Register of the Leften S. Stavrianos Papers, 1942-1963
Hoover Institution Archives
Leften S. Stavrianos Papers,
1942-1963
73088
Stavrianos, Leften Stavros
5 manuscript boxes 2.1 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Writings, press releases, press translations and digests, reports, memoranda, clippings, and pamphlets, relating to political and military developments in Greece and Cyprus, especially during the Greek civil war period, 1944-1949. Includes material collected by a member of the Allied Mission for Observing Greek Elections of March 31, 1946
Administrative Information
Access
Collection open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1973.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Access Points
Elections--Greece; Trade-unions--Greece; Cyprus; Cyprus--Politics and government; Greece; Greece--Foreign relations--United States; Greece--History--Civil War, 1944-1949; Greece--Politics and government--1935-1967; United States--Foreign relations; United States--Foreign relations--Greece
Biographical Note
Stavrianos, Leften Stavros 1913-
1913, Feb. 5 Born, Vancouver, B.C., Canada
1937 Ph.D., Clark University
1937-38 Lecturer, Queens University
1939 Royal Society of Canada traveling fellow
1939-1946 Instructor, then Assistant Professor, Smith College
1944 Author, Balkan Federation
1944-1945 Research and analysis branch, Office of Strategic Services
1946-1956 Associate Professor, Northwestern University
1951-1952 Guggenheim Fellow
1952 Author, Greece: American Dilemma and Opportunity
1953-1954 Ford Faculty Fellow
1956-1973 Professor of History, Northwestern University
1958 Author, The Balkans Since 1453
1962 Author, A Global History of Man
1966 Author, The World Since 1500
1970 Author, The World to 1500
1971 Author, Man's Past and Present
1971-1972 Fellow, East-West Center, Hawaii
1972-1973 Fellow, Center for Advanced Study in the Behavioral Sciences
1973- Professor of History, Emeritus, Northwestern University
Series Description
- Writings, 1948-1957. (Box Box No. 1.)
  Drafts and printed copies of writings arranged alphabetically by title.
- Subject File, 1942-1963. (Box Box No. 1 -4.)
  Press releases, press translations and digests, reports, memoranda, clippings, pamphlets, election material, minutes, and correspondence, arranged alphabetically by subject.
Container List
- Writings, 1948-1957.
  - Antecedents to the Balkan revolutions of the Ninteenth Century, published article, December 1957. (Box 1.)
  - Bibliographical article; present-day Greece, published article, June 1948.
  - Book reviews, general.
  - Greek National Liberation Front (EAM): a study in resistance organization and administration, published article, March 1952.
  - Jews of Greece, published article, October 1948.
  - Mutiny in the Greek armed forces, April, 1944, published article, December 1950.
  - Political Significance of the Working Class Movement in Greece, manuscript draft.
  - Price of Freedom, book review.
  - Two points of view; The immediate origins of the Battle of Athens, American Slavic and East European Review, December 1949.
  - United States and Greece; the Truman doctrine in historical perspective, published article.
- Subject File, 1942-1963.
  - Allied Mission for Observing Greek Elections (AMFOGE), March 1946 (materials collected by American observer Peter Topping). (Box 1.)
    - Issuances of.
      - Instructions, forms and information for observing the elections.
      - Press releases.
      - Press section, Athens. Extracts from the Greek press.
      - Translations from the local press (Northern Greece).
    - Reports, memoranda received by, from various individuals and groups.
      - National Liberation Front (EAM).
        - Central Committee, Athens.
        - Units in Northern Greece.
      - Miscellaneous.
    - Miscellaneous material collected by. (Box 2.)
      - Great Britain. Consulate General, Salonika Press Department. Salonika Press Review.
      - Great Britain. Embassy, Athens. Press Department. Athens Press Summary.
      - Greek government, various agencies.
      - Map of Bulgaria and Northern Greece.
      - Miscellaneous election material.
      - National Liberal Party.
      - National Liberation Front (EAM).
        - Foreign Press Section. Daliy press review.
        - Foreign Press Section. Weekly press review.
        - Miscellaneous.
      - National Party of Greece.
      - National Political Union Party.
      - Populist Party.
      - United Nations Relief and Rehabilitation Administration (UNRRA), Greece Mission, Office of Public Information. Daily news digest.
      - United States Information Service (USIS), Athens. Press review.
  - American Council for a Democratic Greece, 1944-1947.
    - General.
    - Press releases.
  - Balkans, historical background. (Box 3.)
  - Biographical material.
  - Civil war in Greece, 1944-1949.
  - Communist Party of Greece (KKE).
  - Concentration camps in Greece.
  - Cyprus, 1946-1958.
  - Economic conditions in Greece, 1953-1960.
  - Economic, political and social conditions in Greece, 1943-1954.
  - Espionage trials in Greece, 1952-1960.
  - Foreign journalists in Greece during the Civil War.
    - George Polk case.
    - Suppression of news.
  - Foreign support for the Greek rebels, 1948.
  - German documents (in English) on the German occupation of Greece, 1943-1944.
  - Gluecksburg monarchy in Greece.
  - Greek children during and after the Civil War. (Box 4.)
  - Greek Orthodox Church, 1948.
  - Jews in Greece.
  - Labor movement in Greece, 1944-1950.
  - Land reform in Greece.
  - League for Democracy in Greece.
  - Macedonia.
  - Miscellaneous.
  - National Liberation Front, Greece (EAM).
    - Foreign Press Section, March 1947.
    - Miscellaneous documents.
  - National Mutual Aid, Greece (EA).
  - Politics and government in Greece, 1942-1948, 1958-1963.
  - Provisional Democratic Government of Greece, formation of, December 1947.
  - United Nations aid to Greece, 1945-1947.
  - United States aid to Greece, 1947-1956.
  - United States foreign and strategic policy, 1947-1951.
  - World War II, Greece.